## FELIPE SAAVEDRA

Santiago, Chile | (+56) 9 5333 5909 | felisaav@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/felipesaavedra

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Transformational leader & innovation "trader", with +15 years of cross-cultural/functions experience. From engineering, analytics to HR, leadership, mentorship & agile mindset. My value proposition is to combine best practices, diversity of experiences, analytics and leadership in different industries and contexts creating great teams who love their work and reach great results

#### **EDUCATION**

## PONTIFICIA UNIVERSIDAD CATÓLICA DE CHILE

Big Data & Machine Learning Diploma

# NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY - MCCORMICK SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING

Master of Engineering Management - GPA: 3.9/4.0

- Outstanding Academic Performance
- Experience/Certificate in decision making based on information

# UNIVERSIDAD DE CHILE - ESCUELA DE CIENCIAS FÍSICAS Y MATEMÁTICAS

Industrial Engineering - GPA: 6.0/7.0

- Outstanding Academic Performance
- Marketing Engineering TA
- Quantitative Analysis Design Researcher Retail product predictive model

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## TELEFÓNICA HISPAM (TELECOM, €7.9BN)

People Planning & Analytics Regional Senior Manager

- Led people strategic planning, budgeting, analytics and information management processes, at Latin American region level (+8 business units, +30K employees, +€800MM)
- Led efficiency people plan at regional level, resulting on +€95MM decrease in cost
- Led consolidation process of budget & communication of key people metrics
- Led people analytics center of expertise, resulting on people datawarehouse & governance, people data visualization strategy/deployment, analytics use cases: reduce voluntary attrition rate in critical areas/roles, improve performance of B2B sales rep predicting high performance candidates

#### TELEFÓNICA CHILE (TELECOM, €1.7BN)

HR Planning Senior Manager

- Led talent adquisition process, compensation & total rewards, organization design, payroll, people analytics/control and support of union negotiations
- Coordinated People Strategic Planning Process at local level, based on corporate guidelines and local context. From design to initiatives implementation and status keeper
- Led transformational people company programs: reskilling operational process, talent adquisition program (trainee program), local agile office, B2B commercial career development program, gender equality policy and workforce planning program
- Led HR digital transformation. Main goals: E2E process optimization, self-managed employee relationship and decrease HR operational focus

#### LA ARAUCANA (FINANCIAL SERVICES, €90MM)

Strategic Turnaround Team Leader – Strategic Planning and Control Senior Manager

- Led design and execution of turnaround corporate strategy:
  - O Counterpart of financial institutions, regulator, board and unions. Resulting on company financial viability and new corporate bond
  - o Optimization of sales and general expenses, restructuring process and organization, resulting on CLP\$20.000MM/yr OIBDA
  - Optimization of credit sales, with focus on profitable segment, resulting on CLP\$40.000MM FCF in 5 months
- Led design & implementation of business intelligence unit. Resulting on new credit scoring, customer segmentation strategy and campaigns and one source of truth.

SANTIAGO, CHILE

SANTIAGO, CHILE

Jan 2020 - Jan 2021

CHICAGO, IL, US

SANTIAGO, CHILE

2011 - 2012

2000 - 2005

Apr 2021 – Currently

SANTIAGO, CHILE Dec 2016 - Mar 2021

SANTIAGO, CHILE

Feb 2013 - Nov 2016

# TELEFÓNICA CHILE (TELECOM, €1.7BN)

Strategic Planning Senior Analyst / Coordinator

- Aug 2009 Jul 2011
- Led strategic planning integrated model, improving key business driver analysis and market evolution
- Coordinated strategic plan 2011-2013 fixed business unit. Resulting on marketing/sales objectives and financial forecast
- Coordinated strategic project business cases, resulting on financial forecast, mid-term business unit goals and board recommendations

## PRINCIPAL FINANCIAL GROUP (FINANCIAL SERVICES, €118MM)

SANTIAGO, CHILE

SANTIAGO, CHILE

Financial Planning Analyst Jul 2008 - Aug 2009

- Designed forecast models for three high growth business units, improving key business drivers and mid-term goals
- Designed company budgeting process, resulting on integrated and automatic system.
- Implemented 2009-2012 financial projections, with monthly business unit detail and ROE headquarters commitment

#### CONSORCIO SEGUROS (FINANCIAL SERVICES, €1.5BM)

SANTIAGO, CHILE

Sep 2006 - Jul 2008

Actuary

- Designed car insurance actuarial model. Resulting on new technical/commercial policy and improvement on accident rate
- Designed 2008-2010 actuarial forecast to non-life insurance business units, with an annual and three years business unit objectives
- Actuarial/financial analysis of survival and disability insurance, resulting on board recommendations

## UNIVERSIDAD DE CHILE – DEPARTAMENTO DE INGENIERÍA INDUSTRIAL

SANTIAGO, CHILE

Research Assistant

Dec 2005 - Sep 2006

 Designed SKU level forecast demand model, based on category attributes, for a retail Company. Created deep understanding of demand behavior, correlation and marketing drivers on selected categories

#### **SKILLS**

- IT: SQL, Power BI/Tableau, Python/R, Office, Visual Basic, Stata, @Risk, Simio, SAP
- Languages: English (Professional competence) y Spanish (Native)
- Awards: "Executive of the year 2013" (Business Intelligence Chile Community— Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile), Outstanding Academic Achievement (Master of Engineering Management), Advance Human Capital Chilean Program (100% scholarship master degree), High potential professional (Telefónica)
- Courses / Certificates:
  - o People Analytics How to build a talent advantage | Stanford University | Jun Aug 2022
  - o Closing the Gap Between Strategy and Execution | MIT Sloan School of Management | 2020
  - O Digital Business Strategy | MIT Sloan School of Management | 2019